Princetoniana Committee Oral History Project Records, 1994-2015: Preliminary Finding Aid AC259
University Archives
Princetoniana Committee Oral History Project Records
1994-2015
University Archives
Princeton University. Alumni Council. Princetoniana Committee
Princeton University. Library. Special Collections
AC259
5 boxes
The Princetoniana Committee was formed by the Alumni Council in 1981 with the mission of proactively collecting worthy items of Princetoniana on the University's behalf. The Princetoniana Committee Oral History Project (POHP) Records consist of oral history interview transcripts from two separate oral history projects and related materials.
Scope and Contents
The Princetoniana Committee Oral History Project (POHP) Records consist of oral history interview transcripts from three separate oral history projects and related materials. The first set of transcripts consists of interviews with prominent Princeton Alumni assembled for the 1996 book Going Back: An Oral History of Princeton. Also included are correspondence pertaining to the project and audio recordings of interviews. The second set of transcripts consists of oral history interviews undertaken by alumni to capture various aspects of Princeton's history and includes Old Guard alumni, early alumnae, and others with significant Princeton connections. The project started in 2006 and is ongoing. Also included are interview release forms for the interview subjects. The third oral history project centers around individuals who lived in the Butler Apartments graduate students housing.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection consists of multiple accessions donated by members of the Princetoniana Committee [AR.2004.082, AR.2006.011, AR.2007.077, AR.2008.092, AR.2013.127], though Series 2 oral histories are added continually.
Appraisal
Appraisal has been conducted according to University Archives policies and procedures.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital files of some of the transcripts in Series 2 and Series 3 are accessible in the contents list.
Biographical / Historical
The Princetoniana Committee was formed by the Alumni Council in 1981 with the mission of proactively collecting worthy items of Princetoniana on the University's behalf. Since that time the Committee's efforts have broadened to include sporadic exhibits, oral history projects, and a webpage containing information about Princeton traditions.
Universities and colleges -- Alumni and alumnae -- New Jersey -- Princeton.; Interviews.; Audiocassettes.; Compact discs.; Princeton university; Princeton University. Alumni and alumnae.; Princeton University. Alumni Council; Princeton University. History.; Baker, James Addison, 1930-; Cain, Dean; Carril, Pete; Gesner, Clark; Kazmaier, Dick; Kopp, Wendy; Noor, Queen, consort of Hussein, King of Jordan, 1951-
- Series 1: Oral History Interviews for Going Back: An Oral History of Princeton, 1994-1996; 1 box (Box 1)
  Conditions Governing Access
  The collection is open for research use.
  Scope and Contents
  Series 1 consists of interviews with prominent Princeton Alumni assembled for the 1996 book Going Back: An Oral History of Princeton. Also included are correspondence pertaining to the project and audio recordings of interviews.
  Arrangement
  The arrangement of the records at the time of donation has been retained.
- Series 2: Princetoniana Committee Oral History Interviews, 1977-2015 May 12; 3 boxes
  Series 2 consists of oral history interviews undertaken by alumni to capture various aspects of Princeton's history and includes Old Guard alumni, early alumnae, and others with significant Princeton connections. The project started in 2006 and is ongoing. Also included are interview release forms for the interview subjects. Digital files of several of the interview transcripts are accessible in the list below. Additional transcripts will be added as they become available in digital format.
  Transcripts are arranged alphabetically by interviewee's last name.
  - Charles Allen '45, 2007 August 31; 1 box (Box 2)
    Biographical / Historical
    Charles Allen, Class of 1945. Served as Alumni Trustee in 1978 to 1982. Allen majored in School of Public and International Affairs (contemporary Woodrow Wilson School). His father was class of 1915 and his grandfather was class of 1875.
    In the interview Allen discusses the bell in Nassau Hall signaling the start of classes; "Iron Bounds" bicker strategy; debates over destroying older style architecture; Pearl Harbor; World War II; accelerated classes; Princeton ROTC shipped out to Fort Bragg in 1943; being a part of the first Princeton ROTC class to go to Officer Candidate School, Officer Candidate Class107; combat experience in the Philippines; serving on a committee to nominate alumni trustees and serving as Alumni Trustee from 1978 until 1982; and the recruitment of basketball player Bill Bradley. Allen mentions Bill Van Cleve, Walter "Buzzer" Hall, "Beppo" Hall, President of St. Louis Country Day School Bill Edwards, Neal Rubinstine, Arnie Berlin, Bill Bowen, and Pete LeLand.
  - James Amick '45, 2011 June 18; 1 box (Box 2)
    James Amick, Class of 1949. Amick majored in chemistry. He received his M.A. in 1951 and his Ph.D. in 1952 from Princeton in physical chemistry.
    In his interview, Amick discusses growing up during the Depression in Bound Brook, New Jersey; military activity at Princeton; V-J Day on campus; being part of a minority on campus not in an eating club; Chapel Choir; lack of racial diversity; coeducation debates; the experience of his Czechoslovakian Jewish roommate, Louis Berger; living in Middle Reunion; freshmen stealing the clapper from Nassau Hall bell and sophomores trying to stop them; working at Brookhaven in Long Island, RCA Laboratories in Switzerland and Somerville, Exxon Research in Elizabeth, and Mobil in Boston; the undergraduate versus graduate school experience; the Maxwell Mansion fire; and the construction of Firestone Library. He mentions Professors Hubert Newcombe Alyea, John Turkevich, Carl Weinrich, President Dodds, Jim Hillier, and Laurence Chalmers.
  - John L. Armitage '38, 2013 January 13; 1 box (Box 2)
    John L. Armitage, Class of 1938.
    Armitage provides details of his involvement in campus activities including ROTC and varsity crew and football. Other topics addressed in the interview are attending Lawrenceville High School, his membership in Cannon Club, coeducation, and personal contributions to the university. He mentions Professor Hubert Newcombe Alyea, Princeton football player Mickey McPhee, and Princeton wrestler Charlie Powers.
  - James Axtell, 2007 February 23; 1 box (Box 2)
    James Axtell is the author of The Making of Princeton University, published in 2006, and the essay collection, The Pleasure of Academe, published in 1998. He majored in history at Yale, graduating in 1963. He has worked as a professor at the College of William and Mary.
    In the transcript, Axtell explains that Princeton's lack of recorded modern and oral history inspired his book. He discusses the contents of his book as ranging from extracurricular activities to insights into subcultural groups through an anthropological lens; using Princeton Alumni Weekly publications, Bill McCleery's "University: A Princeton Quarterly," the Wertenbaker Papers, and questionnaires to alumni and staff in writing his book; the gaps caused by the war in Princeton's published history; Princeton's hard-working faculty; the negative nature of the eating club system; Woodrow Wilson's introduction of preceptors; the success of the graduate school; and the establishment of the Institute of Advanced Study.
  - F. Tremaine Billings '33, 2007 June 11; 1 box (Box 2)
    Tremaine "Josh" F. Billings, Class of 1933, majored in Biology. He won the Rhodes Scholarship in 1933 and attended Johns Hopkins Medical School, receiving his M.D. in 1938. He served as Class President, Class Secretary, Class Treasurer, and Class Agent. He taught at Meharry and Vanderbilt. He was a member of the American Clinical and Climatological Association medical society and served as secretary.
    In the transcript, Billing discusses his varsity sport involvement in football as a captain senior year, and in wrestling and lacrosse; serving as a doctor in the war; being followed by the Japanese during a war assignment; the efforts of his abolitionist grandfather; getting polio; his wife, who was a flapper; the precept system; the controversial 1933 cow beer jacket design by Bob Wynn and Burt Brush; the issues while Chairman of Student Council during the first Princeton Lit. censorship supported by President of Prudential Life and Chairman of the Board of Trustees at Princeton Edward Duffield; and becoming good friends with Dean Gauss and Dean Eisenhart and their wives on account of the Princeton Lit. censorship. He mentions Tom Smith '33, football Coaches Crisler, and Tad Wyman, Stas Malisewski, Patricia Owaru, Orin Boyce, and Bob Keidle.
  - David Billington '50, 2012 April 26; 1 box (Box 2)
    David Billington, Class of 1950, majored in Engineering. He holds the following distinctions: Gordon Y.S. Wu Professor of Engineering, Emeritus, Professor of Civil and Environmental Engineering, Emeritus, and Lecturer with the rank of Professor in Civil and Environmental Engineering. He won the Fulbright for Engineering to study bridges in Belgium in 1950. He holds honorary degrees in Humane letters from Union College (1990), from Grinnell College in Science (1991), and from Notre Dame University in Engineering (1997). He wrote Robert Maillart's Bridges, and The Tower and the Bridge. He has honorary membership with the American Society of Civil Engineers, ACI, and IASS, membership with NAE, and a fellowship at AAAS.
    Billington discusses his participation in the "Basic Engineering" program; the post-World War II student population; being a member and Vice President of Quadrangle Club; becoming the Princeton Engineering Association's youngest executive committee member; differences between American and European engineering; teaching night classes to Princeton grad students; creating CE262, an engineering-aesthetics course with Robert Mark, using Robert Maillart as the cornerstone; creating a popular introductory engineering course, CE 102; construction of the EQuad in 1962; and setting up an engineering exhibition at the Art Museum. He mentions family friend Dean Kenneth Condit, Chairman of the Music Department Roy Welch, Jim Smith, Freddy Buechner, Gustave Magnel, Robert Mark, Presidents Goheen and President Shapiro, Deans Condit, Elgin, and John, and Associate Dean Ahmet Cakmak.
  - Reg Bishop '44, 2011 June 18; 1 box (Box 2)
    Reg Bishop, Class of 1944, was a French Literature major. He received a Ph.D. in French Literature in 1952 and taught at Princeton and Rutgers, where he became the Dean of Humanities. He served as a full-time lieutenant in the Army in 1943.
    Bishop describes growing up in Springfield; attending Episcopal Academy; coeducation; dating a girl from Princeton; mandatory church attendance; the chapel, First Church, and Trinity; discrimination faced by his Jewish roommate, Lou Kraft; entering the Army during sophomore year; graduating on time despite the war; accelerated classes; ROTC with all of his classmates; the Battle of the Bulge; and the "superb" monthly U.S. Army-run courses. He mentions his thesis advisor and the head of the French Department Ira Wade, President Dodds, and classmates Don Bryant and Herb Hobler.
  - Dr. W. Michael Blumenthal *53 *56, 2014 June 12; 1 box (Box 4)
    Dr. W. Michael Blumenthal received his B.A. from the University of California, Berkeley (1951), and an M.P.A. and Ph.D. in the Woodrow Wilson School from Princeton University (1953, 1956). He served as a Princeton University Trustee in the 1970s and a Berlin University Trustee. He served as Secretary of the Treasury from 1977 to 1979.
    In his interview, Dr. Blumenthal talks about immigrating to the U.S. for college; his Jewish Prussian refugee identity; noticing little Jewish discrimination in the U.S.; teaching introductory economics precepts; receiving a grant from the Social Science Research Council for research in Germany; joining the Bendix Corporation and serving eventually as CEO; working for the State Department and White House; serving as Secretary of Treasury; the cohesiveness of Princeton's alumni and trustee board; the "network of old boys" characteristic of the Princeton community; and creating the Blumenthal Family Fund for tuition aid. He mentions Presidents Bowen, Richard Lester, Alan Blinder, Les Chandler, Fred Harbison, Gardner Patterson, and Bob Goheen; Dean Don Wallace of the Woodrow Wilson school; and confrontations within the Department of Economics and Sociology between Professors Marion Levy and Mel Tumin.
  - John Bogle '51, 2013 February 6; 1 box (Box 2)
    John Bogle, class of 1951, founded of Vanguard mutual fund, and wrote several books including The Little Book of Common Sense Investing and John Bogle on Investing: The First 50 Years. He received an Honorary Doctor of Laws from Princeton in 2005.
    Bogle discusses growing up as part of a well-known family in Montclair during the depression; receiving a scholarship to Blair Academy boarding school; running the Princeton football ticket office; the difficulty of getting good grades at Princeton; writing his thesis, "The Economic Role of the Investment Company;" key elements and recommendations from his thesis becoming Vanguard's founding principles; being awarded magna cum laude for his thesis; describes Vanguard as the only "mutual mutual fund company around;" being hired by Walter Morgan, founder of Wellington Management Company, after Morgan read his thesis; his mistakes while working for Wellington Management Company; starting Vanguard in 1974; writing and dedicating The Little Book of Common Sense Investing; the private school and preppy culture at Princeton; creating a scholarship fund for Princeton students; his relationships with Bogle Scholarship recipients at Princeton; building and dedicating Bogle Hall; being one of the few students that needed to work while at Princeton; supporting coeducation and increasing diversity at Princeton; the effect of the McCarthy era on campus; social life and going out to Billy Golden's bar; his membership in Elm Club; the disparate political environment on campus; and the Princeton alumni community. He mentions Dr. Carroll C. Pratt; John McPhee class of 1953; thesis adviser Philip W. Bell; classmate and winner of a Nobel Prize in Economics, Gary Becker; and classmate Otto Eckstein.
  - Frederick Borsch '57, 2013 May 16; 1 box (Box 2)
    Frederick Borsch, class of 1957, served as a University trustee, the Dean of the Chapel at Princeton from 1981 to 1988, and Interim Dean of Religious Life in the Spring Semester of 2007. He is the author of the book Keeping Faith at Princeton. Interview date: May 16, 2013.
    In his interview, Borsch discusses his late admittance to Princeton; attending Princeton with his roommate from high school in Hinsdale; the private versus public high school student divide at Princeton; the southern culture at Princeton; the isolating environment at Princeton if one lacked money and connections; the lack of diversity in the staff and student body; playing intramural sports; the division in the student body between engineers and liberal arts majors; students' grades posted publicly in Alexander Hall; the one to seven grading system; the desire not to appear "too religious," or a "Christer;" being very sick at Princeton with a lung illness; being sophomore class president; President Dodds' emphasis on the Religion Department; the religious makeup of the student body; Bob Goheen advocating for the Aquinas Foundation; getting rid of the chapel attendance requirement; the impact of the Civil Rights Movement on campus; 20% of the faculty being Jewish; the difficulty of serving as Dean of the Chapel and supporting religious life on campus; Episcopalianism vs. Presbyterianism on campus; the Princeton Evangelical Fellowship; Christian students trying to convert Jewish students on campus; the Princeton Blairstown Center; the difficulty of being Muslim on campus; plans for the Center for Jewish Studies; starting the Center for Jewish Life; and going on to serve as bishop of Los Angeles. He mentions Professor D.W. Robertson or "Robbie," roommate and classmate David Sofield, Presidents Bowen and Goheen, Wilson scholar Arthur Link, Dean Gordon; Harold and Vivian Shapiro.
  - John Brightman '55, 2008 October 10; 1 box (Box 2)
    John Brightman, Class of 1955, served as the annual giving group chair and President of the St. Louis Princeton Club from 1975 to 1977 (the contemporary Alumni Association).
    Brightman describes attending St. Louis Country Day School and attending Princeton with 7 classmates; the coeducation debate; working for St. Louis Union Trust; the emergence of the Orange and Black Club and Blue and Gold Club; fundraising for Princeton; having the nickname "father of the Orange and Black Club; Alumni Schools Committee involvement; selling Princeton themed ties for the Princeton Club; interacting with Heisman Trophy winner Dick Kazmaier in the classroom; football games; getting bursitis sophomore year; playing varsity baseball sophomore to senior year; the evolution of the Princeton Club of St. Louis; problems with the Princeton Club; and Princeton in the College World Series in 1952. He mentions classmate Scott McVey, alum Peter McCarthy of the St. Louis Union Trust, alums and Board of Trustee members Bill Maritz and Jim McDonald, alum Pete Leland, former head of the Alumni Council Don Griffin, and Bill Van Cleve.
  - Professor Victor Brombert, 2013 February 19; 1 box (Box 2)
    Victor Brombert is the Henry Putnam University Professor of Romance Languages and Literatures and Comparative Literature, Emeritus. He graduated from Yale in 1948, and received his M.A and Ph.D. from Yale (1949, 1953). He taught at Yale and was Chairman of the Department of Romance Languages for 25 years. He became a Princeton professor in 1975, and served as the Director of the Gauss Seminars, the Chairman of the Council of Humanities, and the President of the Modern Language Association in 1989. He received the President's Award for Distinguished Teaching at the 1999 Commencement, was a Fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, and a member of American Philosophical Society. He wrote Trains of Thought: Memories of a Stateless Youth, 2002, his memoir, and Musings on Mortality: From Tolstoy to Primo Levi
    In his interview, Professor Brombert discusses his childhood in Paris during World War II and his Russian family escaping Europe in 1941 on a banana freighter; giving the Gauss Seminar on Flaubert in 1964; President Bowen's development of the Target of Opportunity recruitment program; the Battle of the Bulge; teaching undergrad and grad seminars; and his parents' experience during the Russian Revolution. He mentions Yale Professor and personal mentor Henri Peyre, Ralph Freedman and Bob Fagles of the Romance Languages and Comparative Literature Department; Princeton Professors Earl Miner, Joseph Frank, Lionel Grossman, Suzanne Nash, and Francois and Carol Rigolot.
  - Donald Bryant '44, 2011 June 18; 1 box (Box 2)
    Donald Bryant, Class of 1944, majored in Political Science.
    Bryant discusses growing up in Trenton; attending Blair Prep School; living in Hill Dormitory and Pyne Hall; Freshmen Commons; ROTC; fighting in World War II; accelerated classes; being called out of school for active duty in 1942 and to Fort Sill and Fort Bragg in 1943; living in the Little Hall barracks; classmates dying in combat; sailing on the Queen Mary to England; the Dinky; the Missouri Club for tutoring; attending Penn Law School in 1946; the precept system; Princeton's intellectual atmosphere; classmate pranks; Pearl Harbor; required religious service attendance; the integration of Jewish students; drinking on campus; having girls over; Residential College Advisors; classes in McCosh Hall; the Mather sundial; wearing lederhosen during Reunions; and supporting coeducation and the admittance of African-Americans. He mentions Dean of Freshmen Hermance, the Caruthers family, St. Paul's Quitman Chaplain Beckley, Professor "Buzzer" Hall, and classmates Bob Cartotto, Major Bishop, Geg Buttenheim, and Herb Hobler.
  - Alfred Bush, 2010 December 15; 1 box (Box 2)
    Alfred Bush was the Curator of Western Americana at Firestone Library from 1962 to 2002. He graduated from Brigham Young University in 1957, where he majored in Archeology. Before coming to Princeton, Bush worked at the Institute of Archival and History Management at Harvard.
    Bush discusses growing up in Colorado; working with the Jefferson Papers at Princeton; writing a monograph on the life portraits of Jefferson; discovering the lost 1800 portrait of Remembrant Peale of Jefferson in a closet in Peabody Institute at Baltimore; the Rollins collection and Firestone Jim Bridger Room; building the Utah and Mormon collection at Firestone; Dr. Thorington's, '15, endowment of the Mormon Americana collections; Princeton's Aztec and Mayan manuscripts; Princeton's Western Americana Collection; working with Susie Poole to acquire the Blue Lake Papers from Taos Pueblo; Grolier Club trips to New York; the evolution of the Western Americana collection world; increasing the acquisitions budget; connections to Hopi and Tesuque tribes; Princeton's 1970 Ford Foundation grant for convocation of American Indian scholars; and recruitment of and difficulties faced by Princeton's Native American students. He mentions Julian Boyd, Yale's George Kubler and George Miles, President of the Association of Indian Affairs Alfonso Ortiz, collectors Thomas Streeter and Robert Taylor, Native American students Regis Pecos, Ken Romero, Roberto Garcia, and Adae Romero, and collection contributors David McAlpin and Ulli Steltze.
  - Edgar M. Buttenheim '44, 2011 May 5; 1 box (Box 2)
    Edgar "Geg" Buttenheim, Class of 1944, received the Phi Beta Kappa key and earned a Bronze Star at the Battle of the Bulge.
    Buttenheim details growing up in Yonkers; attending Taft School and going to Princeton with 12 classmates; accelerated classes; serving as the Princetonian's business manager; the Princeton Bulletin replacing the Princetonian; ROTC and Enlisted Reserve Corps; entering the Army in 1945; going to Germany with the North Atlantic Treaty Organization Army; living in 1901 Dorm with ROTC; teaching at Hotchkiss School; being a part of the Executive Office of the Headquarters Battery of the 44th Field Artillery Battalion; the "gang bang" incident in Campbell Hall; rooms for rent for girls visiting during football weekends; the campus reaction to Pearl Harbor; being a Quadrangle Club member; the "ironbound" for eating club registry; and the visit of Presidential candidate Wendell Willkie. He mentions Professors "Buzzer" Hall, Frank Graha, and McCabe, President Dodds, and Professor and Ford Chief Executive Lundy.
  - Brendan Byrne '49, 2010 January; 1 box (Box 2)
    Brendan Byrne, Class of 1949, served in the Air Force during World War II. He graduated from Harvard Law School in 1950. He became acting Secretary to the Governor in 1956 and served as Acting Prosecutor of Essex County.